Satsang with Mooji
Episode 5
The
Emptiness of the Emptiness
After this morning,
as an outsider,
you have left me completely
empty,
completely without any future,
without any past,
without any image.
So where am I?
That's right.
Somebody said, that was watching this morning,
or one of the people around here said,
how am I going to get
out of bed in the morning?
Oh, yes.
No, I think that's fairly easy.
That question of getting out of bed in the morning
is fairly simple.
Because
I have to get up and do things.
Life demands that I act,
not just stay in bed
for the rest of my life.
You see,
I have been left as an outsider,
who is viewing all this,
who is listening to all this,
a sense of
blank wall.
A sense of blank wall.
A sense of...
I understand what you have said very...
because it has been very clear to me.
I have...
at one glance,
I have rejected
all the systems,
all the gurus,
the Zen Buddhism, this Buddhism,
this meditation, that meditation, and so on.
I have discarded all that,
because I have understood
the meditator is the meditation.
I have...
But I still feel...
have I solved my problem of sorrow?
Do I know what it means to love?
Do I understand what is compassion?
Not understand, intellectually I can
spin a lot of words.
But at the end of all this,
these dialogues,
after discussing with you all,
listening to you all,
have I this sense of
astonishing energy,
which is compassion?
And end of my sorrow.
Do I know what it means to love somebody,
love human beings?
Actually love.
Actually, actually.
Not talk about it.
No, no, that's all.
I have gone beyond all that.
And you haven't shown me what death is.
Yes.
You have...
I haven't understood a thing about death.
You haven't talked to me about it.
So there are these things.
我说
看吧
before we finish this evening.
A lot of ground to cover.
Could we begin on the question of death?
Yes. Let's begin on that.
One point occurred to me. We discussed in the morning...
saying that we had come to the point...
where when we see the observer as the observed...
then that is death, essentially, is what you said.
Right. Now, this raises a question.
If the self is nothing but an
image, then what is it that dies?
You see, if the image
dies, that's nothing, that's not death.
So is there something real that dies?
There is a biological death.
We are not discussing that at the moment.
You were discussing some kind of death.
When we were talking this morning...
I was trying to point out
if there is no image at all...
if there is no...
variety of images in my consciousness...
there is death.
That's the point that's not clear.
What is it that has died?
You see, death implies something has died.
Died? The images have died. Me is dead.
But is that a genuine death in the sense...
Ah, that's what I want to... Of course.
That's what I want to... Is it a verbal comprehension?
Yes, or more deeply, is
there something that has to die?
You see, I'm trying to...
I'm trying to say something real.
Something.
Yes, in other words, if an organism dies...
I say, I see that, to a point.
Something real has died, you see.
Yes, something real has died.
But when the self dies...
Ah, but I have accepted so far...
the self has been an astonishingly real thing.
Yes.
You come along, you three come along and tell me...
that that image is fictitious.
And I understand it.
I understand it.
And I'm a little frightened that when that dies...
when there is no image, there is...
you follow, there is an ending to something.
Yes, well, what is it that ends?
Ah, quite.
What is that ends?
Because is it something real that ends?
Or you see, you could
say an ending of an image...
is no ending at all, right?
At all.
If it's only an image that
ends, that's an image of ending.
I mean, I'm trying to say that nothing much ends...
if it's only an image.
Yes, that's what I want to get at.
Is that... you know what I mean?
If it is merely an ending of an image...
Right, then there's nothing much.
There is nothing.
No, it's like turning off the television.
That leaves me nothing.
Right.
Is that what death is?
Or is there something deeper that dies?
Oh, very much deeper.
Something deeper that dies?
Yes.
Well, how about the image-making process?
Would you want to...
That's a question.
No, no, I would say...
it is not the end
of the image, which is death...
but something much deeper than that.
But it's still not the
death of the organism, you see.
Still not the death of organism.
Because the organism, we know all that.
Will go on up to a point.
Up to a point, yes.
Disease, accident, old age or senility and so on.
But death...
is it the ending of the image...
which is fairly simple and fairly...
you know, acceptable and normal...
but logically or even actually...
but that...
yes, but it's like a very shallow pool.
Yes.
You have taken away the little water...
and there is nothing but mud left behind.
There is nothing.
So is there something much more?
That dies?
No.
Not that dies, but the meaning of death.
Well, is there something more than the image that dies...
or does death have a meaning
beyond the death of the image?
Of course, that's what we are asking.
That's the question.
That's what we are asking.
Is there something about death...
that is bigger than the death of the image?
Obviously, it must be.
Will this include the death of the organism, this meaning?
Yes.
Death of the organism might go on...
I mean, the organism might go on...
but eventually come to an end.
Yes.
But if we were to see
what death means as a whole, universally...
then we would also see what
the death of the organism means.
Yes.
And is there some meaning also
to the death of the self-image?
The same meaning.
That's only, I should say,
that's only a very small part.
That's very small.
Right.
That's a very, very small part.
But then, is there, say...
one could think there might
be the death of the self-image...
then there might be a process...
or a structure beyond the self-image that might die...
and that creates the self-image.
Yes, that is thought.
That's thought.
Now, are you discussing the death of thought?
Yes, that's only also again superficial.
That's very small.
Very small.
And is there something beyond thought in us that should...
That's what I want to get at.
We are trying to get at the meaning of death...
We are not quite clear.
Yes, which is beyond the death
of the self-thought or the image.
No, just look. The image dies.
The image...
That's what I want to get at.
It's fairly simple.
Right.
It is a very shallow affair.
Then there is the ending of thought...
which is the ending of dying to thought.
You say thought is deeper than the image...
but still not very deep.
Not very deep.
So we have removed the maker of image...
and the image itself.
Right.
Now, is there something more?
In what sense something more?
Something more that exists or something more...
that has to die?
Is it something creative that happens?
No, no. We are going to find out.
But I mean your question is not clear...
when you say, is there something more?
Is there... No.
Is that all death?
Is that death?
Oh, I see. Is that all that death is?
Me, yes.
This is death.
No, no. I understand image, maker of image.
Right.
But that's a very shallow affair.
Right. So then there is something else.
And I say, is that the meaning of death?
Right. I think I am getting with you.
Is that the meaning of
death only in that little part?
Or is there a meaning that is bigger?
Death must have something enormously significant.
Now you are saying death has a meaning...
significant for everything, for the whole of life.
Whole of life.
Yes. Now, first could you say...
why do you say it? In other words...
at first it is not generally accepted...
if we are thinking of the viewer...
that death is that sort of thing.
In other words, the way we live now...
death is at the end.
And you try to forget about it...
and try to make it unobtrusive and so on.
But if you...
as you three have worked at it, pointed out...
my life has been in a turmoil.
And my life has been in constant conflict, anxiety...
all the rest of it.
That has been my life.
I have clung to the known.
And therefore death is the unknown.
So I am afraid of that.
And you come along, we come along and say...
look, death is partly the ending of the image...
the maker of the image...
and death must have much greater significance...
than merely this...
empty...
saucer.
Well, if you could make it more clear...
why it must have, you see.
Why it must have, because...
Why must it?
Is life just a shallow empty pool...
empty mud at the end of it?
Why would you assume it is anything else?
I want to know.
But even if it is something else...
I have to ask, why is
it that death is the key...
to understanding that, do you see?
Because it is the ending of everything.
Everything.
Reality.
And all my concepts, images...
end of all the memories.
That is in the ending of thought, right?
Ending of thought.
And also it means ending of time.
Ending of time.
Time coming to a stop totally.
And there is no future...
in the sense of past
meeting the present and carrying on.
I mean psychologically speaking.
Yes, psychologically speaking. Of course.
We are psychologically speaking.
We still admit the future on the clock.
Of course.
Right. Okay.
Ending, psychological ending of everything.
Right.
That is what is death.
And when the organism dies...
then everything ends for that organism.
Of course.
When the organism, this organism dies...
it is finished.
But wait a minute.
If I don't end the image...
the stream of image-making goes on.
Yes. Well, again it is not
too clear where it goes on.
Do you see, in other people or in...?
It manifests itself in other people.
That is, I die.
Right. Organism.
I die, the organism dies...
and at the last moment...
I am still with the image I have.
Yes. So then what happens to that?
That is what I am saying.
That image has its continuity...
with the other rest of the images.
Your image, my image.
Right.
Your image is not different from mine.
Right. We share that.
No, no. Not share it. It is not different.
Right. I get you.
It may have a little more frills...
a little bit more colour...
but essentially the image, my image is your image.
Right.
Yes.
Now, so there is this constant flow of image-making.
Well, where does it take place? In people?
It is there. It manifests itself in people.
Oh, you feel that it is broader...
in some way it is more general, more universal.
Yes, much more universal.
That is rather...
I say it is rather strange,
I mean, to think of that.
Yes.
It is there.
It is a stream.
It exists. Like a river.
Like a river, it is there.
And it manifests itself in streams...
And people.
...which we call people.
No, that stream is the maker of images and images.
Right.
So, in other words, you are saying...
the image does not originate only in one brain...
but in some sense it is universal.
Universal, quite right.
It is not clear. You are not only saying...
that it is just the sum
of the effects of all the brains.
No. But are you implying something more?
It is the effect of all the brains...
Yes.
...and it manifests itself in people as they are born...
genes and all the rest of it.
Now, is that all?
That is... Yes, that is a yes.
Does death leave me...
me, I mean, does death bring about this sense of...
enormous, endless energy which has no beginning and no end?
You...
Or is it just...
I have got rid of my images...
and the image-maker is... I can stop it.
It is very simple.
I can be stopped and... Yes.
But I haven't touched much deeper things.
There must be... Life must have infinite depth.
Yes, now the death which opens that up...
Death opens that up.
...is the death, you say, of the...
but we said it is more
than the death of the image-making.
You see, this is what is not clear.
Is there, for example, I am trying to say...
something real which is...
blocking that from realising itself.
Yes.
It is blocking itself through image and thought-maker.
That is what is blocking it, though.
The image-making and thought-making...
is blocking this greater. Yes.
Wait, wait. Blocking that.
Blocking that, right.
But there are still other blocks, deeper blocks.
That is what I was trying to get at.
There are deeper blocks that are real.
That are real. Now...
That is... And they really have to die, aren't they?
That is just it.
So would that be like this stream...
that you are talking about that is there?
No, no. There is a stream of sorrow, isn't there?
Yes. Now, in what sense?
Is sorrow deeper than the image?
Yes. It is.
That is important. It is.
You think so? Don't you?
I do. I think so.
No, no. Be careful, sir. This is very serious.
That is right. That is right.
I mean, would you say...
sorrow and suffering are the same...
or just different words?
Different words. Sorrow and suffering.
Just to clear it up.
Deeper than this image-making is sorrow.
Isn't it?
Man has lived with sorrow a million years.
Well, could we say a little more about sorrow?
You see, what is it? It
is more than pain, you see.
Oh, much more than pain.
Much more than loss.
Much more than losing my son
and my parent, or this or that.
It is deeper than that.
It is much deeper than that.
It goes beyond the image, beyond thought.
Beyond, of course. Beyond thought.
Beyond what we ordinarily call feeling.
Oh, feeling, thought. Now, can that...
Well, let me... before you go...
are you saying that the stream of
sorrow, if I can be so naive...
is a different stream from the stream of image-making?
If you had to say it
is there, is it two different streams?
No, it is part of the same stream.
Part of the same stream, but much deeper.
Much deeper.
I was saying then, there is a very deep stream...
image-making is on the surface of this stream, right?
That's all.
The waves on the surface, right?
But we have been left with that.
You see, I want to penetrate...
Well, could you say we have
understood the waves on the surface...
of this stream which we call image-making?
Image-making. That's right.
And whatever disturbances in sorrow...
comes out on the surface as image-making.
That's right.
So now we have got to go deep sea diving.
Right? River driving.
Right.
But what is...
You know, sir...
there is universal sorrow.
Yes, but let's try to make it clear.
It is not merely the sum
of all the sorrow of different people.
No, no. It is this...
Could we put it this way?
The waves on the river...
doesn't bring compassion.
Or compassion, love would be synonymous...
so we will keep to the word compassion.
The waves don't bring this.
What will, without compassion...
without compassion...
human beings can't...
as they are doing, they are destroying themselves.
So, is...
does compassion come...
with the ending of sorrow...
which is not the sorrow created by thought?
Yes, all right.
So, in thought you have sorrow for the self, right?
Yes. Sorrow for the self.
Which is self-pity. Self-pity.
And now you say there is another...
I think we haven't quite got hold of it.
There is a deeper sorrow.
Which is universal, not merely the total sum...
but rather something universal.
That's right.
What is that? Can we spell that out?
Essential.
Spell that out. Go into that.
Don't you know it?
Yes.
Without my... I am just asking.
Don't you know or aware...
of a much deeper sorrow...
than the sorrow of thought, self-pity...
the sorrow of the image?
Yes.
Ah?
Does this sorrow have any content?
I mean to say it's
sorrow for the fact that man...
is in this state of affairs
which he can't get out of.
That's partly it.
That means partly the sorrow of ignorance.
Yes. I mean that man is
ignorant and cannot get out of it.
Cannot get... You follow?
Yes.
And that the perception of that sorrow is compassion.
Right.
So the non-perception is sorrow then?
Yes. Yes.
Are we seeing the same thing?
No, I don't think so.
Say for instance you see me in ignorance.
I see the whole mankind.
Mankind in ignorance.
Right.
And after living millennia they are still ignorant.
Ignorantly in the sense we are talking.
That is, maker of the image and all that.
Now let's say that if my mind is really good...
clear, that should have a deep effect on me.
Yes. Right?
Yes. What would have a deep effect?
To see this tremendous ignorance.
This tremendous destruction.
We are getting at it. We are getting at it.
We are getting at it.
Right.
But then if I don't fully perceive...
if I start to escape the perception of it...
then I'm in it too.
Yes, you are in it too.
But the feeling is still...
that universal sorrow is still something that I can feel.
I mean, is that what you mean to say?
Yes.
Although I am not very
perceptive as to what it means.
No, no, no.
You can feel the sorrow of thought.
The sorrow of thought. But I can sense...
or somehow be aware of the universal sorrow.
Yes, you can. Right.
You say the universal sorrow is there...
whether you feel it.
You can feel it. You can feel it.
Feel it or sense it. Right.
Right.
The sorrow of man living like this.
Is that the essence of it?
I'm just moving into it. Let's move into it.
Is there more to it?
Much more to it.
Oh, well. Then perhaps we
should try to bring that out.
I'm trying to.
There is...
Sorrow, yes.
You see me.
I live the ordinary life.
Image, sorrow, fear, anxiety, all that.
I have the sorrow of self-pity.
Right.
All that.
And you who are enlightened, in quotes...
look at me and say, aren't
you full of sorrow for me?
Which is compassion.
I would say that is a kind of energy...
which is tremendously aroused because of this situation.
Yes. Right?
Yes.
But would you call it
sorrow? Or you call it compassion?
Compassion, which is the outcome of sorrow.
But have you felt sorrow first?
I mean, has the enlightened
person felt sorrow and then compassion?
No.
The other way?
No, no, no. Be careful.
I'll go very carefully.
Which is...
You see, sir, you are saying...
that one must have sorrow first to have compassion.
I'm just exploring.
Yes, we are exploring.
Through sorrow you come to compassion.
That's what you seem to be saying.
Yes, I seem to be saying.
But which implies...
that I must go through all
the horrors of mankind in order.
Right.
No.
No? No.
But let's say...
That's the point, sir.
Let's say the enlightened one, the enlightened man...
sees this sorrow, sees this destruction...
and he feels something, he senses something...
which is a tremendous energy.
We call it compassion.
Now, does he...
he understands that the people are in sorrow...
Of course.
But he is not himself in sorrow.
That's right.
But he feels a tremendous energy to do something.
Yes. Tremendous energy of compassion.
Compassion, feeling for them.
Compassion.
Would you then say that he...
that the enlightened man...
perceives or is aware of...
the...
I hate to use the word inefficiency...
but the conflict, the...
the...
he is not aware of sorrow...
he is aware of the awkwardness...
the blundering, the loss of life.
No, sir.
Dr. Shainberg, just listen.
You...
have been through all this.
Suppose you have been through...
all the...
Sorrow.
Image, thought, the sorrow of thought...
the fears, the anxieties...
and you say, I've understood that.
It's over in me.
But you have left very little.
You have energy.
But you have... it's a very shallow business.
And is life so shallow as all that?
Or...
has it an immense depth?
Depth is the wrong word.
Well, yes, inwardness.
Inwardness.
And to find that out...
don't you have to die...
to everything known?
Yes.
But how does this relate
to sorrow at the same time?
I'm coming...
You might feel...
I'm ignorant.
I have my anxieties, all the rest of it.
You are beyond it.
You are on the other side
of the stream, as it were.
Don't you have compassion?
Yes.
I do.
I see that.
Not up here.
No, I know.
But I see it and I...
Compassion.
Yes.
Is that the result of the ending of sorrow...
universal sorrow?
What? Universal sorrow?
Universal sorrow.
Wait, let's say the ending of sorrow.
Now, that's not the end of the world.
That's the end of the world.
Now, you are talking about the person...
who was in sorrow to begin with.
Yes.
And in him this universal sorrow ends.
Is that what you are saying?
No, no.
More than that.
More than that. Well, we have to go slowly.
Because if you say the ending of universal sorrow...
the thing that is puzzling
is to say it still exists.
You see, if the universal sorrow ends...
then it's all gone.
Ah, it's still there.
It's still there.
You see, there is a certain puzzle in language.
So, in some sense the universal sorrow ends...
but in another sense it persists.
Yes. Yes, that's right.
But could we say that if you have an insight...
into the essence of sorrow, of universal sorrow...
then in that sense sorrow ends in that insight.
Yes, that's right.
Although it goes on.
I've got a deeper question, though.
The question is...
I don't think you have understood.
I think I understood that one...
but my question comes before...
which is...
is that here is me...
the image-making has died.
That's the waves.
Now, I come into the sorrow.
You've lost the sorrow of thought.
Right.
The sorrow of thought is gone...
but there is a deeper sorrow.
Is there?
Or are you assuming there is deeper sorrow?
I'm trying to understand what you are saying.
No, no.
I'm saying...
is there compassion...
which is not related to thought?
Or is that compassion born of sorrow?
Born of sorrow.
Born in the sense...
when the sorrow ends there is compassion.
Okay.
That makes sense.
That makes it a little clearer.
When the sorrow of thought...
Not personal sorrow.
Not the sorrow of thought.
Not the sorrow of thought, but something deeper.
Something deeper.
When that sorrow ends...
then there is a birth of compassion.
Of compassion, of energy.
Now...
Is there not...
a deeper sorrow than the sorrow of thought?
Well, there is the...
David was saying...
the sorrow for ignorance is deeper than thought.
The sorrow for the universal...
calamity of mankind trapped in this sorrow.
The sorrow of a continual repetition of wars and history...
and poverty and people mistreating each other...
that's a deeper sorrow.
That's deeper than the sorrow of thought.
And it is.
Can we ask this question?
What is compassion?
Which is love.
We are using that one
word to cover a wide field.
What is compassion?
Can a man...
who is in sorrow, thought, may...
can he have that?
He can't.
Absolutely cannot.
Right?
Yes.
Now, when does that come into being?
Without that, life has no meaning.
You have left me without that.
So, you...
if all that you have taken away from me...
is superficial sorrow...
thought and image.
And I feel there is something much more.
I mean, just doing that leaves something empty...
or meaningless, right?
Something much greater than this shallow little business.
Is there...
when we have thought producing sorrow, self-pity...
but also the realisation of the sorrow of mankind...
and could you say the energy which is deeper...
is being in some way...
Moved.
You see, well, first of all, in the sorrow...
this energy is caught up in whirlpools or something.
You see, it's much deeper than...
it's deeper than thought...
but there is some sort of very deep disturbance...
of the energy, right?
Yes, quite right, sir.
Which we call deep sorrow.
Deep sorrow.
Ultimately, it must...
its origin is the blockage in thought though, isn't it?
Yes, that is deep sorrow of mankind.
Yes, the deep sorrow of mankind.
For centuries upon centuries...
it's like a vast reservoir of sorrow.
It's sort of moving around in some way that's disorderly...
Yes.
...and preventing clarity...
and so on. I mean perpetuating ignorance.
Ignorance, perpetuating ignorance, right.
Because, you see, if it were not for that...
then man's natural capacity to learn...
would solve all these problems. Is that possible?
That's right.
Right, right.
Unless you three give me...
or help me or show me or have an insight...
into something much greater...
I say, yes, this is very nice...
and I go on. You follow?
Yes.
What we are trying to do,
as far as I can see...
is to penetrate into something beyond death.
Beyond death.
Death, we say, is not
only the ending of the organism...
but the ending of all the...
ending of the content of the consciousness...
and the consciousness...
which we know as it is now.
Is it also the ending of sorrow?
Ending of sorrow of that kind...
of the superficial kind.
That's clear.
Yes.
And a man who has gone through all that...
he said, that isn't good enough.
You haven't given me the flower, the perfume...
you've just given me the actress of it.
And now, we three are trying to find...
that which is beyond the ashes.
Right.
You say there is something...
there is that which is beyond death.
Absolutely.
Would you say that is eternal?
I don't want to use the word...
You won't use the word, but in some sense...
beyond time.
Beyond time.
Therefore, eternal is not the best word for it.
Therefore, there is something
beyond this superficial death...
as eternal.
A movement that has no beginning and no ending.
But it is a movement.
It's a movement.
Movement not in time.
What is the difference between a movement in time...
and a movement out of time?
Sir, that which is constantly renewing...
constantly...
new is in the word...
constantly fresh...
flowering...
endlessly flowering...
that is timeless.
This whole flowering implies time.
Yes, well, I think we can see the point.
I think we get that.
The feel of renewal and creation...
and coming and going without transition...
without duration, without linearity...
that has...
You see, let me come back
to it in a different way.
Being a normally fairly intelligent man...
read various books...
tried various meditations...
Zen and this and that and the other thing...
at one glance I have an insight into all that.
At one glance. It's finished.
I won't touch it.
And it may be...
the ending...
of this image-maker and all that...
there a meditation must take place...
to delve...
to have an insight...
into something which mind has never touched before.
Right.
But I mean, even if you do touch it...
then when you...
That doesn't mean the next time it will be known.
It can never be known.
It's always new in some sense.
Yes, it's always new.
It is not a memory stored up and altered, changed...
and call it new.
It has never been old.
I don't know if I can put it that way.
Yes, I think I understand that.
It's old.
Could you say it like a
mind that has never known sorrow?
Yes.
It might seem puzzling at first...
but you move out of this state...
which has known sorrow...
into a state which has not known sorrow.
Yes, that's right.
In other words, there is no you.
That's right.
Can we say it this way too?
Could we say that it's an action...
which is moving...
where there is no you?
You see, when you use the word action...
action means not in the future or in the past...
action is the doing.
Yes.
Most of our actions are the result of the cause...
or the past, or according to your future.
Right. This is not that.
That's not action, that's just conformity.
No, I'm talking about a different kind of action.
No, I wouldn't... action implies...
...a certain kind of action.
Yes.
You see, there are several things involved.
To penetrate into this...
the mind must be completely silent.
Right?
Otherwise you are projecting something into it.
Right. It is not projecting into anything.
Absolute silence.
And that silence is not the product of control.
It is wished for, premeditated, predetermined.
Right.
Therefore that silence is not brought about through will.
Right. Right?
Right.
Now, in that silence...
there is...
there is this sense of...
something beyond all time...
death, all thoughts, you follow?
Something...
Yes.
Nothing.
Not a thing. You understand?
And therefore empty, and therefore tremendous energy.
And moving.
Energy. Leave it, leave it.
Is this also the source of compassion?
That is what I... That is it.
What do you mean by source?
Well, that this...
in this energy is compassion, is that...
Yes, that is right.
And in this energy...
This energy is...
...is compassion. That is different.
Of course.
This energy is compassion.
See, that is different than saying the source.
You see, and beyond that there is something more.
Yes. Beyond that.
Of course.
Beyond that. Well, why do you say of course?
I don't know.
What could it be that is more?
Sir, let's put it a little differently.
Everything thought has created is not sacred.
It is not holy.
Yes, well, because it is fragmented.
It is fragmented. We know it.
I am putting up an image...
of worshipping. It is a creation of thought.
It is made by the hand or by the mind.
It is still an image.
So in that there is nothing sacred.
Because as you pointed out, it is...
thought is fragmented, limited, finite.
It is a product of memory and so on.
So there is nothing sacred.
It is the sacred therefore that which is without limit.
That is it.
I mean...
There is something beyond compassion...
Beyond compassion.
...which is sacred.
Yes.
Or is it beyond movement?
Sacred.
You can't say movement or non-movement.
You can't say anything.
A living thing...
you can only examine a dead thing.
A living thing you can't examine.
What we are trying to do
is to examine that living thing...
which we call sacred, which is beyond compassion.
What is our relation to the sacred then?
To the man who is ignorant, there is no relationship.
Right?
Which is true.
To the man who has removed the image, all that...
who is free of the image and the image-maker...
is still... it has no meaning yet.
Right?
It has meaning only when he goes beyond everything...
beyond... he dies to everything.
Dying means in the sense...
never for a single more second accumulating anything...
psychologically.
But would you say...
would you say that there is any...
you asked the question, what
is the relationship to the sacred?
Is there ever a relationship to
the sacred or is the sacred...
No, no, no, he is asking something.
He is asking what is the relationship between...
that which is sacred, holy, and to reality.
Yes, well, that's implicit anyway.
I mean, that's implied.
Of course.
That...
We've talked about it some time over, this question.
Which is, reality which is the product of thought...
has no relationship to that.
Because thought is an empty little affair.
That may have a relationship with this.
In some way, yes.
Right.
And the relationship comes through insight...
insight, intelligence, and compassion.
How does the... how... how...
what is that relationship?
I mean, what is intelligence, I suppose, we are asking?
Intelligence? What is intelligence?
I mean, how does intelligence act?
Wait, wait.
You have had an insight into the image.
You have had an insight into the movement of thought.
Movement of thought which is self-pity, creates sorrow...
and all that.
You have had a real insight into it.
Haven't you?
It's not a verbal agreement or disagreement...
or logical conclusion.
You have had a real insight into that business...
into the waves of the river.
Now, have you an insight also...
isn't that insight intelligence?
Right.
Which is not the intelligence of a clever man...
we are not talking of that.
So there is that intelligence.
You have already got that intelligence.
That's right.
Now, move with that intelligence...
which is not yours or mine.
Intelligence.
Not Miss Dr. Shenberg or Case...
or somebody's.
It is universal intelligence.
Global or cosmic intelligence.
That insight.
Now, move further into it.
Move with it.
Have an insight into sorrow...
which is not the sorrow of thought...
the enormous sorrow of mankind...
of ignorance. You follow?
Yes.
And then, out of that, insight, compassion.
Now, insight into compassion.
Is compassion the end of all life?
End of all death?
It seems so, because you have...
you follow? You have thrown away...
mind has thrown away all the burdens...
which man has imposed upon itself.
Right?
So you have that tremendous feeling...
a tremendous thing inside you.
Now, that compassion...
delve into it.
And there is something sacred...
untouched by man.
Man, in a sense, untouched by his mind...
by his cravings, by his demands...
by his prayers, by his everlasting chicanery...
tricks.
And that may be the origin of everything...
which man has misused.
You follow?
Yes.
Not that it exists in him...
because then we get lost.
But if you say it
is the origin of all matter...
or all nature...
Of everything, of all matter, of all nature.
Of all mankind. Yes.
That's right, sir.
I'll stick by it.
So, at the end of this dialogue...
I want to ask you...
what have you...
what has the viewer got?
What has he captured?
What would we hope he'd captured?
Or what would you say...
what have we hoped that he would capture?
Or what has he actually captured?
What has he actually... not hoped.
Right.
What has he actually captured?
Has he... has his bowl filled?
Filled with the sacred.
Or he says, well, I've
got a lot of ashes left...
very kind of you...
but I can get that anywhere.
Any logical, rational human being says, yes...
by discussing, can wipe out all this...
and I've left nothing.
Or has he got...
Yes, that's what...
he has come to you...
I have come to you three...
wanting to find out...
transforming my life...
because I feel that is absolutely necessary...
not to, you know, get rid of my ambition...
all the silly stuff which mankind has collected...
I empty myself of all that.
I... please, when I use the word I...
it's not...
I can't empty itself.
I... it dies to all that.
Now, have I got anything out of all this?
Have you given me the perfume of that thing?
Can I give you the perfume?
Or...
Yes, sir.
Share it with me.
I can share it with you.
Has the viewer shared with us...
the experience we've had being together?
Have you, too, shared this thing with this man?
Right.
Have we shared this with this man?
If not, then what? What?
A clever discussion.
Dialogue.
Oh, that we are fed up.
You can only share when you are really hungry.
You follow?
Burning with hunger.
Otherwise you share words.
So I've come to the point...
we have come to the point when we see...
life has an extraordinary meaning.
Yes, well, you say it has a meaning far beyond...
what we usually think of.
Yes, this is so shallow and empty.
But would you say this sacred is also life?
Yes, that's what I was getting at.
Ah...
Life is sacred.
And the sacred is life.
And have we shared that?
Have you shared that?
So we mustn't misuse life.
You understand?
We mustn't waste it because our life is so short.
You follow?
You feel that each of our
lives has a part to play...
in this sacred which you talk about.
What, sir?
Each of our lives has an important part...
in some sense to play.
It's part... it's there.
It's a part of the whole.
Yes.
And that misusing it is...
well, to use it rightly has a tremendous significance.
Yes, quite right.
But to accept it as a theory...
is as good as any other theory.
Right.
There's something though...
I feel troubled.
Have we shared it?
Yes, sir.
That burns... that question burns.
Have we shared the sacred?
Which means really...
all these discussions and dialogues...
have been a process of meditation.
Right.
Not a clever argument...
a real penetrating meditation...
which brings insight...
into everything that is being said.
Well, I should say that we have been doing that.
I think we have been doing that.
We've been doing that.
Yes.
And have we shared that?
With whom? Among ourselves?
With the viewer.
Well, I should say that's a difficult...
Are you considering the viewer...
or are you considering...
or...
there is no viewer at all?
Are you speaking to the viewer...
or...
only that thing...
in which the viewer...
you and I...
everything is?
You understand what I'm saying?
We've got two minutes more.
Well, how would you respond then...
what David said? He said...
we have been in a...
you say we have been...
and I say we've been in a meditation.
How have we shared in our meditation?
No. I mean... no.
Has it been a meditation?
Yes.
This dialogue?
You know, meditation is not just argument.
No, we've shared. I feel that.
Seeing the truth of every statement...
or the falseness of every statement...
or seeing in the false the truth.
Right. And aware in each of us...
and in all of us...
of the false as it comes out and is clarified.
See it all.
Therefore we are in a state of meditation.
Right.
And whatever we say...
must then lead to that ultimate thing.
Then you're not sharing.
What are you?
There is no sharing. We've got one moment.
There is no sharing. It's only that.
That.
The act of meditation...
is that.
No, there is no...
there is only that. Don't...
Okay.